Guide to the National Alliance of Russian Solidarists: correspondence and photographs collection M1909
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
National Alliance of Russian Solidarists: correspondence & photographs
circa 1930-1990
M1909
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
1.0 Linear feet
Scope and Contents
Includes 150 photographs of NTS activists and events associated with NTS activities, circa 1930-1989. The correspondence includes letters to N.B. Tarasova, 1962-1982, circa 155 pages from Sergei Rafal'skii, 70 pages from Anatolii Darov + unpublished poems, 12 pages from Nina Fedorova, 12 pages from Leonid Rzhevskii, and 10 pages from Nikolai Arsen'ev + unpublished poems. Other batches of correspondence include 200 pages of letters to the chairman of NTS, V.M. Baidalakov, to V.D. Poremskii, and others, and there are some 390 letters and postcards to the editorial office of the weekly Posev.There is also a 136-page typescript by N.S. Kozorez, "About service in a Cossack encampment and 10 ears in Stalin's camps."
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2012.
Biographical/Historical note
The National Alliance of Russian Solidarists (“Народно-Трудовой Союз российских солидаристов” or NTS) is a Russian émigré political organization founded in Belgrade in 1930 by a young generation of exiled Russians. It soon spread to other European capitals, and during the course of the next 50 years, it became the largest and the most active Russian émigré political organization, having its center in Western Germany. The ideology of the NTS was based on anti-communism. The main accent was on the belief that the Soviet system was incapable of evolution, and therefore it needed to be removed by means of internal opposition. The other principle of the ideology of the NTS was solidarism, built largely on the NTS’s understanding of the ethical code of Christianity. The NTS stressed the collective social responsibility of people for the welfare of others, and it praised the principle of national and international solidarity against the communist idea of class struggle. The NTS defended democratic participation in government. Its platform included an appreciation of human rights and the idea of individual freedom and personal responsibility. The NTS proposed to solve the problem of socialism versus capitalism by articulating an ideology which placed itself “beyond right and left”.
The members of the NTS were politically active, striving to find the best ways of creating and underground revolutionary force in Soviet Union and using the following means to try to achieve its goals: sending its people into the Soviet Union covertly; clandestinely distributing propaganda leaflets; setting up radio station. NTS members were strongly opposed to the Soviet regime, but they felt close to the Russian culture and people. The publishing of books and other literature became one of the distinguishing features of all the activities run by NTS. In 1945, the first NTS publishing house, the Russian language press Posev, was created in Germany in the refugee camp Monchehof, located in the Kassel district in the State of Hessen. In 1947, Posev moved its headquarters to Limburg (Limburg an der Lahn); in 1952 it moved to Frankfurt am Main. Over the years, 300 books were published by Posev, and the weekly journal Posev and the literary magazine Grani gained excellent reputations. Not only anti-communist propaganda articles were published, but also highly valued literary works. Between 1960 and the the end of the 80-ties, about 170 titles by dissident authors from the Soviet Union were published by Posev. It can be said that the activity of Posev penetrated the Iron Curtain in both directions, and it contributed immensely to the collapse of Soviet Empire in 1989.
This collection contains materials regarding Posev’s “Limburg” period (1947-1952), and it also contains the correspondence between the editors and several authors (1949-1976). Exceptional value can be attributed to the photograph collection (150 are dated from 1936 to 1983). Most of the photographs have been identified, and they constitute a rich source for future researchers interested in the history of the NTS. Vladimir Semenovich Batshev (Batchev) is a Russian writer who has lived since 1995 in Germany.
Arsenev, Nikolai Sergeevich, 1888-1977; Artemov, Aleksandr Nikolaevich, 1910-; Baidalakov, Viktor Mikhailovich, 1900-1967; Darov, Anatolii, 1920-; Galich, Aleksandr Arkadevich, 1918-1977; Gorachek, Vladimir IAromirovich, 1916-1981; Mirkovich, Elizaveta Romanovna, 1918-1994; Okolovich, Georgii Sergeevich, 1901-1980; Olgskii, Mikhail Leonidovich, 1912-1998; Ostrovskii (Romanov), Evgenii Aleksandrovich, 1914; Poremskii, Vladimir Dmitrievich, 1909-1997; Rafalskii, Sergeii Milievich, 1895-1981; Redlikh, Roman Nikolaevich, 1911; Rzhevskii, Leonid Denisovich, 1905-; Siniavskii, Andrei Donatovich, 1925-1997; Sorokin, Pitirim Aleksandrovich, 1889-1968; Svetlanin, Andrei Vasilevich, 1909-1965; Tarasova, Nataliia Borisovna; Trushnovich, Aleksandr Rudolfovich, 1893-1954; Zalevskii, Mikhail Nikolaevich, 1895-1996
- National Alliance of Russian Solidarists: documents (NTS)
  - SBONR: Soiuz Borby za Osvobozhdenie Narodov Rossii (Union of Struggle for the Liberation of the Peoples of Russia) and SAF: Soiuz Andreevskogo Flaga etc.: 1949 and 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of the Central Administration of the North American Division of NTS with the leaders of NTS, etc.: 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Vestnik Ispolnitelnogo Biuro Soveta NTS: 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ispolnitelnoe Biuro Soveta NTS, 1955: Documents (Box 1, Folder 3)
- POSEV: the publisher and the weekly newspaper: Correspondence
  - 1947: Family names, which start with L, M, N, O, P (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947: Family names, which start with R, S, T, U (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1948: Family names, which start with K, L, M, N, P (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1948: Family names, which start with R, S, T, V, Z (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Individual correspondence
  - Tarasova, Nataliia Borisovna: editor of "Grani": Correspondence with Arsenev, Nikolai Sergeevich, 1975-1976. Unpublished poetry. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tarasova, Nataliia Borisovna: editor of "Grani": Correspondence with Darov, (Dar) Anatolii, 1949-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tarasova, Nataliia Borisovna: editor of "Grani": Correspondence with Rafalskii, Sergei Milich, 1957-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tarasova, Nataliia Borisovna: editor of "Grani": Correspondence with Siniavskii, Andrei Donatovich,1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tarasova, Nataliia Borisovna: editor of "Grani": Correspondence with Rzhevskii, Leonid Denisovich, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Shirinkina, Ariadna Evgeevna: NTS member: Correspondence with Galich (Ginzburg), Aleksandr Arkadevich, 1974. Original manuscript of poem "Primety vesny". (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Poremski, Vladimir Dmitrievich: NTS leader: Correspondence with Sorokin, Pitirim Aleksandrovich, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ostrovskii (Romanov), Evgenii Romanovich: editor of "Posev": Correspondence with Rutchenko, Nikolai Nikolaevich (Rutych), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memoirs. Kozorez, N. S.: 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs
  - Alfman, Aleksandr Vasilevich: 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Artemov (Zaitsev), Aleksandr Nikolaevich: NTS president: 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Artemov (Zaitsev), Aleksandr Nikolaevich: NTS president: 1949, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Baidalakov, Viktor Mikhailovich: NTS president (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Balmashev, Mikhail Vladimirovich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Baranovichi: 1950? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bashkirov, Ivan Sergeevich: NTS member: Bad Homburg, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Berukshtis, Igor: Soviet defector (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Belaia, E. V. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bevad, N. I. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Boldyrev, Konstantin V.: NTS member, "Posev" administration: Mönchhof 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Boldyrev, Konstantin V.: NTS member, "Posev" administration: 3 photographs (1947, 1979) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Breitbart, Ekaterina Elekeevna: editor of "Grani": 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brunst, Dmitrii Viktorovich: NTS member: 193? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brunst, Irina: 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brunst, Lena: 193? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Budakov, IAkov Vasilevich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chernoglazov: Belgrade, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dubrov, Andrei: Soviet dissident (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Durnov: Belgrade, 1938-1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gandziuk, Georgii IAkovlevich: 193? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Garanin, Evgenii Ivanovich: NTS member: Brussels, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gatskevich (Karalin), Vladimir Antonovich, one of the founders of "Posev": Mönchhof 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gorachek, Vladimir IAromirovich: NTS member, POSEV publisher: Mönchhof 1947; 1950, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gorachek, Vladimir IAromirovich: NTS member, POSEV publisher: 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gorachek, Vladimir IAromirovich: NTS member, POSEV publisher: Bad Kissingen, 1981? (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gorachek, Nina Viktorovna: Bad Kissingen, 1981? (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gutan: Washington, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ilenko, Anna Fedorovna: France, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - IUgov, Aleksandr Mikhailovich: NTS member, editor of "Posev" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kalantar, Izabella Aleksandrovna (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kalikin (Dalanian): Washington, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kandaurov, Aleksei Alekseevich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kapulov-Grachev, Vladimir Ivanovich: 2 photographs (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kapulova, Valentina Polikarpovna (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kerenskii, Aleksandr Fiodorovich: 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kessler, Eduard Valentinovich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Khasapov, Valentin: 193? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Khokhlov, Nikolai Evgenevich: defector (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kolin (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kondogrev: Belgrade, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Konstantinoff, George (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kopovei, Anatolii Aleksandrovich (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Krikorian, Sergei I.: translator (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Krushel, Tatiana Aleksandrovna (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kudriavtsev, O. K. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kurilenko, Pavel Stepanovich: 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Labin, Suzanne (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lamzdorff, Grigorii Pavlovich (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lapa: Munich, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lebed (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Levitskii, Sergei Aleksandrovich: Washington, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lushnikov, Arkadii Ivanovich: NTS member: Brussels, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lutsenko (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Malyshev, Aleksei Nikolaevich (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Metius, T., woman: 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mirkovich, Elizaveta Romanovna: NTS member, editor of "Posev"; 2 photographs: E.R.M. and 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Molchanov, V.: Book fair in Franfurt (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mozgovoi, Semen IOsifovich: NTS member: Brussels, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - N. S. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Nashivanenko, Georgii Timofeevich: NTS member: Bad Homburg, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Nashivanenko, Georgii Timofeevich: NTS member: end of 60-ties (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Neimirok, A. N. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Nikolai "Skif": Utrecht, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Nikolskii, Maksim (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Novikov, Adam: Morocco, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Okolovich, Georgii Sergeevich (G.S.O.): NTS leader: Mönchhof 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Okolovich, Georgii Sergeevich (G.S.O.): NTS leader (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Olgskii, Mikhail Leonidovich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Orekhov, V. V. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Orlova, Lidiia Eduardovna, NTS member (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Popov, Kolia: Munich 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Poremskii, Vladimir Dmitrievich, NTS president: 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poremskii, Vladimir Dmitrievich, NTS president (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Poremskii, Vladimir Dmitrievich, NTS president: 2 photographs (1985) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Poremskaia, Tatiana Vsevolodovna: 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poremskaia, Tatiana Vsevolodovna: 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pozdeev, Evgenii Evgeniievich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poze (Poloshkin), Georgii: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Prusse, M. V.: Bad Homburg, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rar, Gleb Aleksandrovich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rar, Lev Aleksandrovich: NTS member, editor of "Posev" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rar, Lev Aleksandrovich: NTS member, editor of "Posev" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Redlikh, Roman Nikolaevich: NTS member, editor of "Grani" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Redlikh, Roman Nikolaevich: NTS member, editor of "Grani": 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Romanov (Ostrovskii), Evgenii Romanovich: NTS prsesident, editor of "Posev": Limburg, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Romanov (Ostrovskii), Evgenii Romanovich: NTS president, editor of "Posev": 5 photographs (1949?, 1958, 1977, ERO) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Romanov (Ostrovskii), Evgenii Romanovich: NTS president, editor of "Posev": Mönchhof 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Romanov (Ostrovskii), Evgenii Romanovich: NTS president, editor of "Posev": 2 photographs (1979, 1985) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rozhdestvenskii, Serafim Pavlovich: NTS member: Tokio 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rusak, Adam Vasilevich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rutchenko (Rutych), Nikolai Nikoaevich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Samarin (Sokolov), Vladimir: NTS member, editor of "Posev" (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sanikova, Zoia S. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Savvich, I. IA.: Besancon, France, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Selinski: Belgrade, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Shebratskii, Stepan IAkovlevich: Besancon, France, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Shits, G. P., woman: 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Shits, Nikolai Fedorovich: NTS member: Mönchhof, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Shits, Nikolai Fedorovich: NTS member: 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Shomotov-Chaplinski, Ivan Ivanovich: 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Shveder, Irina Mikhailovna: Bad Kissingen, 1981? (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Slava "Mrachnyi": 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sorokin, I. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sokolov, Nikolai: Morocco, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Statsevich, Vsevolod Aleksandrovich: NTS member: Brussels, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Stolypin, Arkadii Petrovich: NTS member: 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Stolypin, Dmitrii (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sushko: Washington, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Svetlanin, Andrei Vasilevich: editor of "Posev": 3 photographs (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Svetozarov: Shvetsiia (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tarakanov, Fedor Sergeevich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tarasov, S. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tikhanovich, Viacheslav Andreevich: France, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tretiakov, Vladimir Nikolaevich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tringam: Belgrade, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Trushnovich, Aleksander Rudolfovich: NTS member: 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Trushnovich, Aleksander Rudolfovich: NTS member: 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tsimmerman, Vladimir Sergeevich: Bod Homburg (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tulai (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Vergun, Irina Dmitrievna: 193? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Zalevskii, Mikhail Nikolaevich: NTS member (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Zarechniak: Washington, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Zavzhalov, Dmitrii Mikailovich: Besancon, France, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Zelenskii: Washington, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Zhadan, Pavel Vasilevich: Belgrade, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Zhediliagin, IUii Petrovich: NTS member: Mönchhof, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Zhediliagin, N.: 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Zhestkov, V. P. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified individuals and groups (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Group: NTS members: 1930-ties (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Group: NTS members: France, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Group: NTS members: Besancon, France, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Group: NTS members: Belgrade, 1936, 1939? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Group: NTS members: Meeting of the Closed Sector, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Group: Board of NTS: Mönchhof, 1946; Limburg 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Group: Employees of the publishing office: Limburg (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Group: Employees of the publishing office (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Group: Crew of Soviet ship (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Group: Washington, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Group: Social events, 1950-1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mönchhof: refugee camp, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - NTS activities: meetings, actions, demonstrations (Box 2, Folder 7)